Dostoevsky, poets of the Golden Age,
Достоевский поэты Золотого века
composers, and so on and so forth,
композиторы А и так далее и так далее
who influenced
которые повлияли
uh very much not only
э очень очень сильно на э не только
Russian culture, but also world culture. I
российскую Но и на мировую культуру я
understand correctly that your parents,
правильно понимаю что ваши родители
after a hard day there when they
после там ээ трудового э дня когда они
worked there on their peasant farm, sat down like that  in the evening we read
поработали так садились вечером читали
Dostoevsky, so they put some
Достоевского так ставили э там на
record of Tchaikovsky on the patiphone to
патифон ээ Чайковского пластинку
listen to.
какую-то послушать
Good evening. Hello, I’m from Ukraine,
Добрый вечер Здравствуйте я из Украины
the city of Khmelnitsky. Where are you from? I’m from Bratsk,
город Хмельницкий Вы откуда Я из Братска
Irkutsk region. I see you’re imperi, how
Иркутска область Я вижу вы импери како у
you have it there. If I’m not mistaken, the imperial flag
вас там Если не ошибаюсь имперский флаг
is hanging Yes, on the wall Yes, but  I’m not an imperial And
висит Да на стене Да но я не имперец А
why do you use this flag is
почему этот флаг используете
interesting, well, because this flag
интересно ну потому что этот флаг
belongs to that part of
относится к той части
history which, in my opinion, is the
истории которая Как по мне является
best and most outstanding I
наиболее лучшей и выдающейся
understood from the history of my country I understood But what
понял из истории моей страны понял А вот
region are your
области мои
ancestors from?
предки часть из Украины часть из
part of Chuvashia Uh-huh Ponya From
белорусси часть Чувашии Угу Поня Из
Moscow yes they were at the time when
Москвы да они вот во время когда
this imperial flag was used they
использовался этот имперский флаг они
who were there noble peasants
кем были там дворянами крестьянами в
mostly Christian yes that is, what do
основном Кристиана да то есть а чем вот
you like about that era when your
вам нравится та Эпоха когда ваши
ancestors were still peasants in the Russian Empire
предки были в Российской империи
or serfs even
крестьянами ещ или крепостными даже
this one  the flag was approved under
ещ ну этот флаг был утверждён при
Alexander II, who is called
Александре II которого называют
Alexander the Liberator, who
Александром освободителем который
canceled canceled well canceled what
отменил отменил хорошо отменил в чём
your ancestors lived well in this
жилось хорошо вашим предкам в этой
Russian
Российской
Empire Well let’s
империи Нух
say the economy that is, they were
хозяйство так скажем То есть были
fists What they called later when
кулаками Как называли потом когда пришли
the Bolsheviks came, I understand correctly that having the
большевики я правильно понимаю что иметь
opportunity to do your own farming
возможность заниматься своим хозяйством
is  achievement of the empire No, this is not an
- это достижение империи Нет это не
achievement of the empire, you asked what they were
достижение империи вы спросили чем они
doing, I answered you, I have no idea what
занимались я вам ответил Не име вду чем
they were doing in the Empire, that you are
они таким занимались в Империи что вы
proud of the empire for this, you think
гордитесь империей за это вы считаете
that it was the best period for
что это было там лучший период для
them, I don’t mean that, I
них я имею в виду не тово
mean it  cultural moment, that is,
имею в виду и культурный момент то есть
Dostoevsky, poets of the Golden Age,
Достоевский поэты Золотого века
composers, and so on and so on,
композиторы и так далее и так далее
who
которые
influenced very very much
повлияли очень очень сильно
not only Russian but also world
на не только российскую Но и на мировую
culture, the same Dostoevsky and
культуру того же самого Достоевского и
Tchaikovsky are now being staged from the very
Чайковского сейчас ставят от самого
East, that is, Japan, ending with the very
Востока то есть Японии заканчивая самом
West. That is, I’m correct  I understand that
запа То есть я правильно понимаю что
after working there,
ваши родители после там трудового
when they worked there on their peasant
когда они там по своему крестьянскому
farm, they sat down
хозяйству поработали так садились
in the evening and read Dostoevsky, so they played
вечером читали Достоевского так ставили
some kind of record on Tchaikovsky’s phonograph,
Чайковского пластинку какую-то послушать
maybe yes, either there or went to the Opera x Well,
может да Или там или ходили в Оперу х Ну
I don’t know. Well, that is, I just don’t  I can
я не знаю Ну то есть я просто не могу
understand that your ancestors lived like this and there was
понять вот жили ваши предки так и был
some Dostoevsky and Tchaikovsky that
какой-то Достоевский и Чайковский что
your ancestors got from this Dostoevsky
вашим предкам было от этого Достоевского
Tchaikovsky, they didn’t see him, didn’t hear him,
Чайковского они его не видели не слышали
didn’t read him, didn’t hold him in their hands,
не читали не держали в руках
but perhaps I had people in my family
но возможно у меня были и в роду и люди
who could afford to
которые могли себе позволить
get acquainted  with these
ознакомиться с данными
figures It’s interesting, and on what basis.
деятелями Интересно а на основании чего
You’re making this assumption. That
Вот вы такое предположение делаете Что
Perhaps they were. Well, because,
Возможно они были Ну потому
well, quite a lot, many,
что ну довольно-таки уже много-много
many generations have passed. Uh-huh. That is, it
много поколений прошло Угу То есть
turns out that somehow they were all
получается как-то все были
just noble families; they can somehow be
просто дворянские роды их можно как-то
traced back  Yes, but Christians, it
хоть проследить Да а христианские
turns out, lived there to read. They didn’t know how to
получается жили там читать Не умели
write. They didn’t know how to write well. And for example,
писать Не умели хорошо А например
Dostoevsky. And what is the merit of, for example, the
Достоевский А в чём заслуга например
same tsar? Yes, that Dostoevsky
того же царя Да в том что Достоевский
wrote his
писал свои
works.
произведения
Well, you
Ну
can rely on his biography,
можно опереться на его биографию
perhaps. Well, that is, if you take his
возможно Ну то есть если брать его
biography, then in his youth he  he had
биографию то в молодости он был
quite radical, radical,
довольно-таки радикальных радикальных
anti-tsarist views, so to speak,
про противо царских взглядов так скажем
and after
и после того как
he was sent to hard labor in exile,
он его отправили на каторгу в ссылку а
he completely changed his attitude towards
он полностью поменял своё отношение к
the regime and politics, and so on and so
режиму и к политике и так далее и так
forth, and became, one might say, a completely
далее и стал можно сказать совершенно
different person and after that  wrote
другим человеком и после этого написал
his brilliant works about this
свои гениальные произведения о это
achievement of the tsar in that Dostoevsky
достижение царя в том что Достоевского
was sent to hard labor and he began after
сослали на каторгу и он начал после
you ask. I’m talking about how the tsar
спрашиваете Я говорю как царь
influenced him.
повлиял доста
Look, I just understand that this is
Смотри я просто понимаю так что в этом
the achievement of the tsar that Dostoevsky
достижение царя что Достоевского
was sent to hard labor and he then began
отправили на каторгу и он начал потом
to write after hard labor. Well,  I understood or
писать после каторги Ну так я понял или
not or misunderstood, well, if the tsar had
нет или неправильно понял ну если царь
not done this, then perhaps there would not have been
бы этого не сделал то возможно не было
such a brilliant writer as
бы такого гениального писателя как
Dostoev understood. I liked this turn, it
достоев понял Вот это поворот мне
turns out that maybe the tsar
понравился то получается может царь
did something bad, there should have been even more people
плохо сделал надо было ещё больше людей
for the hag, that is, how many writers
на каргу то есть сколько писателей
Russia has lost,
потеряла росия
he said  about It’s just that it seems to me that
говорил про Просто мне кажется что
Stalin was so consistent, he was very consistent with
Сталин так он был очень последователен
this king, he understood that this is an
вот этого царя он понял что это
effective method of raising culture, the
эффективный метод поднятия культуры чем
more you send to penal servitude and the more will
больше сослать на каторгу да тем больше
appear. Dostoevsky and Stalin
появится Вот таких Достоевский и Сталин
put such people right into the stream,
прямо на поток поставил
referring probably Dostoevsky
ссылался наверно Достоевского секрет
understood the secret But look And now  there are
понял А вот смотрите А сейчас есть
some Russian writers whom you
какие-то российские писатели которых Вы
know, yes, Victor Pelevin about Pelevin, and he, for
знаете да Виктор Пелевин о Пелевин а он
example,
например
writes because Yeltsin or Putin,
пишет из-за того что Ельцин или Путин
in short, referred to him somewhere as
короче его куда-то ссылался
the merit of
заслугой
Pelevin’s uh creativity Yes,
э-э творчества Пелевина Да творчество
Pelevin’s creativity is the merit of Putin and Yeltsin
Пелевина - это заслуга Путина и Ельцина
Oh well  they influenced him Well, they influenced the
Да ну а они повлияли на него Ну повлияли
rain influenced, for example, winter influenced there
дождь повлиял например там зима повлияла
Yes, for example, a drunk neighbor could influence Yes,
Да например пьяный сосед мог повлиять Да
but whose merit in
но Чья заслуга в
this is clear that everything around us it
этом ясно что всё что вокруг нас оно
influences the maintenance of ours there are
влияет на на содержание наших там
some we Duma But man creates
каких-то мы Дума Но человек творит из-за
because  there Yeltsin is doing something with Putin,
того что там Ельцин с Путиным что-то
or the tsar,
делает или царь
or he is doing something because of his own
или он творит из-за своих каких-то
motives. Well, these motives may
побуждений Ну ему эти побуждения могут
come to his mind because of the actions that
прийти в голову из-за действий которые
are happening around him. Uh-huh, I understand, that is, it
происходят вокруг него Угу понял то есть
turns out
получается
that all the writers and singers and
что все писатели и певцы там и
composers are there  who are now or who
композиторы которые сейчас или которые
were then they wrote, they were influenced by
были тогда они писали на них влияли вот
these monarchs, presidents Yes, and under
эти монархи президенты Да и они под
their influence they wrote, did something, created
влиянием их писали делали что-то творили
something Well, influencing someone,
Да ну на кого-то влияя на кого-то
politics, philosophy, someone
политика на кого-то философия кто-то
wrote philosophical treatises  someone wrote
писал философские трактаты кто-то Писал
music, someone wrote, someone went into the
музыку кто-то Писал кто-то шёл в
priesthood and studied theology and
священники и занимался богословия и
interpreted
занимался трактовкой
Well, the Bible and all sorts of different sacred
Ну библии и всяких различных священных
scriptures, and so on and so forth, but what about
писаний и так далее и так далее а что
you, for example, from Pelevin,
что вы например из Пелевина вот такой
you can say such a quintessence of him Well,
квинтесс его можете сказать Ну
Generation P  probably, well, here’s an idea,
Generation P наверно ну вот идея идея
some kind of idea,
какая а
but basically in his works there
Но в основном в его произведениях
is more of a Buddhist
прослеживается больше буддийская
theme. No, what. For example, if
тематика Не ну какая Вот например если
we look at Tolstoy there, there is
там мы смотрим там там Толстого там до
some kind of motive there against
вот какой-то леть мотив там против
tsarism there, for liberation there, or
царизма там за освобождение там илито
that’s the essence of all the writings  Pelevin,
вот какая суть всей писанины Пелевина
that’s what Well, I would probably say refusal
вот что Ну я бы наверно бы сказал отказ
and avoidance
и уход от
somehow explain Yes, well,
как-то объяснить Да ну
from modern goods, you can say so Well,
от современных благ можно так сказать Ну
that is, from consumerism, so to speak,
то есть от потреблятство вот так сказать
that is, spend your time on
то есть тратить своё время на то чтоб
eating as deliciously as possible and as
Как можно вкуснее покушать и как можно
many videos as possible  on YouTube That's how I would
больше видео на ютубере Вот так я бы
say Cool, and Pelevin, by the way,
сказал Прикольно а а Пелевин кстати в
is in the YouTube Len, in my opinion he is not on the EU tube
юбе есть Лен по-моему его нет на тубе ес
if I'm not mistaken feeds
если я не ошибаюсь питает
just how to say it Well, there is debate Does
просто как это сказать Ну ходят споры
he even exist, that is,
Существует ли он вообще вот то есть
among his fans Well, there is someone-  then
среди его фанатов Ну существует кто-то
who writes under the name Pleven, someone
кто пишет под именем плевен кто-то же
is the truth It’s not artificial
есть правда Это же не искуственный
intelligence that generates And they think there are such
интеллект генерирует И думают есть такие
versions And there are versions that this is a group of
версии А есть версии то что это группа
people Yeah, I understand, look, I
людей Вот Угу понял то смотри я
understand correctly that now in order
правильно понимаю что сейчас для того
for Russian culture to
чтобы Российская культура снова
return Dostoevsky again
Достоевский надо вернуть царя
there is no tsar Where is the logical chain I think so,
нет Где логическая цепочка я так я думаю
I can’t understand, so I just understand
я не могу понять вот я просто понимаю
that from our conversation Dostoevsky
что вот Достоевский из нашего разговора
became who he is and began to write such
стал тем кем есть да и стал писать такие
works because he was
произведений из-за того что вот на него
influenced by the era of tsarism, exile there, convict
повлияла Эпоха царизма ссылки там катор
food, then here  how is it possible now, you
еда то вот как сейчас можно вот вы же
keep that flag there too, and how
держите это там флаг тоже да как сейчас
can you now revive this so that new
можно тогда возродить вот это чтоб новые
people can be given freedom of creativity? Wait,
дать свободу творчества людям Подождите
you said exile to hard labor and auntie
вы говорили ссылка в каторгу а тете
Freedom of creativity Well,
Свобода творчества Ну да
yes, Dostoevsky was not exiled for
так его Достоевского сослали не за
his creativity, but he was exiled for his
его творчество а его сослали за его
political
политические
beliefs that he
убеждения что о
participated in explain
участвовал объяснить
Well, something like terrorist
А ну что-то типа террористических
circles, let’s put it that way. That is, I
кружков так скажем То есть я правильно
understand correctly that you can
понимаю что ээ творчеством можно
engage in creativity, but so that it doesn’t slip through the cracks in creativity,
заниматься но чтоб в творчестве не
then it turns out that way, I
проскакивает тогда так получается я вам
repeat to you, he wasn’t engaged in it, he was
повторяю ээ он занимался не его сослали
n’t exiled for creativity, but for that  that he was in a
не за творчество А за то что он был в
terrorist circle that
террористическом кружке которая
was engaged in undermining not just a
занималась Э подрывом не просто
political one, they
политического
will make a living for ordinary citizens
устроят на жизнь обычных граждан
I’m now wondering, well, now I’m googling for a minute
Мне сейчас интересно ну сейчас я минутку
just why he was sucked, well,
на гуглю прям за что он был сосан ну
Dostoevsky became interesting, well, okay,
Достоевский аж интересно стало Ну хорошо
that’s how And now that there is no freedom
вот как А сейчас что нету свободы
of creativity, like, well  why don’t people
творчества типа ну почему сейчас не
like
появляются такие как
Dostoevsky appear now? Well, first of all, people like
Достоевский Ну во-первых таких как
Dostoevsky are one in a million, so Well, if
Достоевский оди на миллионы так Ну если
in Russia there are 140 million 140 Dostoevskys there
в России 140 млн 140 достоевских должно
should already be, well, if you have never
бы быть уже ну если вы никогда не
heard such an expression that is not
слышали тако выражение которое не
literally interpreted, then I
буквально трактуется то мне вас
feel sorry for you, I think you when  they tell you that a
Жаль я думаю вы когда вам говорят что
man got into a galosh I hope you
человек сел в калошу Я надеюсь вы у вас
don’t have enough brains Well, this is what the link writes Although
не так Ну вот так кар ссылка пишет Хотя
Dostoevsky denied the charges against him, the
Достоевский отрицал предъявленные ему
court recognized him as one of the
обвинения суд признал его Одним из
most important criminals for reading and for
важнейших преступников за чтение и за
failing to report the dissemination of a criminal letter about
недонесение о распространи преступного о
religion and government by the
религии и правительстве письма
writer
литератора
Belinsky  Uh-huh Yeah That is, it turns out that
Белинского Угу Ага То есть получается
he,
его
uh, was sentenced for the fact that he,
ээ приговорили за то что он
uh, read, for
ээ читал за
reading, he read, and for the fact that he didn’t snitch
чтение он читал и за то что не настучал
that someone else was distributing, that
о том что кто-то другой распространял то
is, passing on this same publication Yes, a letter from
есть передавал этот самый изда Да письмо
another writer Belinsky
другого литератора Белинского
Uh-huh Yeah, then after all, A  where
Угу Ага то всё-таки А где что
did the terrorist circle explode? Well, I’m not
террористический кружок взрывал Ну я не
saying that he himself
говорю что он непосредственно сам
was directly involved in explosions, and so on and so
занимался взрывами и так далее и так
forth, he was engaged in the dissemination of
далее он занимался распространением
propaganda data, but where? Well, what ones
пропагандой данных ну а где Ну какие вот
I’m trying here now?
я сейчас пробую тут
Well, I don’t see anyone writing here. Well, I came in.
так я не вижу чтобы тут писал Ну зашёл А
Where did you find it?  such that he
где вы нашли такое что он
supported this
был поддерживал вот этот терроризм
kind of terrorism, there’s no
какой-то нету
such thing. I’m interested, I just heard
такого Мне же интересно я просто услышал
this for the first time, I think
такое впервые думаю
damn it, well, you found out
блин ну вы узнали то
that one in a million doesn’t mean exactly
что один на миллион это не значит именно
that one in a million doesn’t That’s what
что один на миллион не Вот про
you said about Dostoevsky, I’m not good at
достоевско вы сказали Я не силён в
history  Russia, yes, but when I heard that
истории России да но когда услышал что
Dostoevsky was being condemned for the fact that he
Достоевского осудить за то что он там в
was in some kind of terrorist circle there,
террористическом кружке каком-то был там
spreading the ideas of terrorism Damn, I did
распространял идеи терроризма Блин я
n’t go in, I didn’t look at all,
зашёл не смотрю вообще
but what? Well, I can’t
другое зато что Ну я вам не смогу сейчас
exactly find the source for you right now. Where did I get this from?
точно найти источник Где откуда я это
I didn’t  I wear about where you
взял Я же не ношу примерно откуда вы это
got it from, you read it in a telegram, or
взяли вот в телеграме прочитали или
that in my opinion it was one
что по-моему это была одна
of the books of his contemporaries, but I don’t
из книг его современников но я уже не
remember who it was. So, well, in
вспомню кого име Так а ну во письмо
Belinsky’s letter, this letter was shorter,
Белинского во это было письмо короче
Belinsky wrote a letter to Gogol, I
Белинский написал письмо Гоголю Я так
understand it or
понимаю или
not, no  not now now now so this is
не нене не сейчас сейчас сейчас так вот
the letter for which Dostoevsky
письмо то за которого за чтение этого
was sent into exile for reading this letter
письма отправили на в ссылку
so
Достоевского так
[music]
[музыка]
for reading the authorities were really
вот за чтение реально власти были
so imbued with reading everyone
настолько проникнуты за чтение всех
was immediately sent to hard labor,
отправляли немедленно на каторгу в том
including Dostoevsky who fell under this Yes In
числе и попал под это Достоевский Да Во
already standing  on the scaffold a few minutes
уже стоя на эшафоте за несколько минут
before the execution, Dostoevsky and other
до казни Достоевский и другие
prisoners heard the words that
арестованные услышали слова о том что
Tsar Nicholas I had mercy and instead of execution there
царь Николай I милует и вместо расстрела
would be penal servitude, and he wasn’t just supposed to be sent to a hag. They should have
будет каторга а его не просто на каргу
shot him, well, yeah,
его вообще должны были Расстрелять ну да
damn it, and then the Tsar thought, I realized that
Ага блин а царь потом дума я понял то
they should  were in favor of reading this
есть их должны были за чтение этого
letter from the writer Belinsky Shoot
письма литератора Белинского Расстрелять
and the Tsar thinks Damn we don’t
а царь думает Блин нам не
have enough These are one in a million,
хватает Таких вот один на миллион
maybe I’ll
каких-то вот Может я этих сейчас чуваков
just send these dudes to hard labor and they’ll
Просто отправлю на каторгу и из них
turn out to be some kind of luminaries there,
получится там вот светила какие-то там
interesting
интересно
Oh, I already explained it to you  the fact
Ой я вам уже объяснил то
that he participated in a circle about the checheskiy
что он участвовал в кружке около ческом
circle can be Who are the Petrovites
кружке може стати Кто такие петровцы
if you want, you can
если хотите можете
google Well, tell me who the Petrovites are
загуглить Ну так скажите кто такие
Well, I’m not going to explain absolutely everything to you, you
Ну я же не буду вам абсолютно всё
can google it, you can
объяснять може загуглить можете
google it, I told you that he
загуглить я вам сказал то что он
participated in a terrorist circle, you
участвовал в террористическом кружке вы
started googling  check with me you can
начали гуглить проверять со мно можете
google
загуглить
yourself
самих
[music]
[музыка]
terrorist circle
террористическом кружке
Well, there are these Petrash, briefly, who were these
Ну есть эти петраша коротко кто эти были
Petrashevites
петрашевцы
Well,
Ну ну
freethinkers with views, freethinkers And who are
вольнодумцы взглядами вольнодумцы А кто
Valen
такие вален
Doom, well,
дум ну
I would probably characterize people
Я наверное бы охарактеризовал людей
who Well, probably think freely,
которые Ну мыслят наверно свободно
taking into account the etymology of the word
учитывая от этимологии слова
Uh-huh That is, it turns out They  were people
Угу То есть получается Они были людьми
who wanted to think freely Yes, I
которые хотели мыслить свободно Да я
understand correctly Well,
понимаю Ну
yes, what’s the joke, yes, what’s the joke of what? Well, that
да в чём прикол то да в чём прикол чего
is, it turns out that you read it to me.
Ну то есть получается вот вы мне
I also discovered the Petrashevites, and
зачитали Я тоже открыл петрашевцы да
like, there’s that
типа там це
uh,
эээ
here’s the Petrashevites, convicted in
вот петрашевцы осуждённые в сорок
1949, participants in the meetings with Mikhail
девятом году участники встреч у Михаила
Butashevich  Petrashevsky Yes, they were
буташевич Петрашевского Да они были
freethinkers
вольнодумцы
Well, what is that Well, freethinking Freedom of
Ну а что та Ну вольнодумство Свобода
thought Well, what’s the joke, but they only
мысли Ну а в чём прикол да только у них
had views of a revolutionary nature
были ре взгляды революционного характера
And what do you mean views of a
А что что имеется в виду взгляды
revolutionary nature
революционного характера
But the fact that they were quite radical in their
Но то что они довольно-таки радикально
attitude towards that current government and
относились к той действующей власти и
they advocated the construction of a
выступали за построение
socialist utopian society,
социалистического утопического общества
and that is, they advocated there, for example, for
а то есть они выступали там например за
some kind of abolition of the monarchy, and yes, and the
какую-то за отмену монархии да да и
construction of socialism, that is, it
построение социализма то есть они
turns out that they were saying that they were being
получается рассказывали что типа их
oppressed, yes.
угнетают да Угу Вот и что нужно было бы
there was a monarchy Yes, that there are
было монархии Да что есть угнетенные
some kind of oppressed classes which are peasants
классы какие-то которые вот крестьяне
What were your relatives like and Dostoevsky
Как ваши родственники были а Достоевский
it turns out that he wanted your great-great-
получается хотел чтобы ваша пра
great-grandmother to be able to read him, to
прапрабабушка могла его читать могла
go to the library, but it turns out that I
ходить в библиотеку да получается что-то
didn’t understand anything at all and what
вообще ни фига не понял да что он такого
did he do so bad I’m here  I just can’t
плохого сделал я вот не могу я просто
when I meet an Imperial I want to understand Why
когда встречаю имперца Я хочу понять Чем
Yes, only I said that I’m not, well, not an
Да только я говорил что я не ну не
Imperial I’m so figuratively calling everyone who
имперец я Я так образно называю всех кто
hangs this flag Imperial like Uh-
вот вешает вот этот флаг Имперский типа
huh Just some kind of damn
Угу Просто какая-то блин фигня
incomprehensible garbage ah
непонятная ай
That is, it turns out yes Streamer
То есть получается да Стример
sry  the channel is called Now I’ll write
сри канал называется Сейчас напишу
and I haven’t looked at the chat yet,
анд я ещё в чатик не заглядывал там
probably
наверно
now there’s something like this in the chat, but I just want to
сейчас такой идт в чате но я хочу просто
understand with this Dostoevsky, just since
вот понять с этим Достоевским просто раз
you said that Dostoevsky was
ты сказал что Достоевский
born in this period because it would be
это годи этим периодом потому что это бы
the other way around, that he was persecuted by
довс наоборот что его преследовали
some kind of garbage  it turns out it’s
какая-то фигня получается
incomprehensible, for
непонятна
example, I opened the biography of this
так например я вот биографию этого
Petrashevsky there so that
Петрашевского открыл там вот терр чтобы
terror terrorism can’t be found at all, there’s not a
террор терроризм найти вообще нету ни
word like that. Well, I’m not sure that it’s possible that
слова такого Ну я не уверен что возможно
at that time such a
в то время вообще существовал такой
term as terrorism existed at all. Well, they write
термин как терроризм не Ну пишут же
Wikipedia now and not
сейчас Википедию а не
then, well, based on this  they don’t write on time,
тогда ну на основе это вовремя не пишут
but Petrashevsky advocated the
вот петрашевский выступал за
democratization of the political system of
демократизацию политического строя
Russia and the liberation of the peasants with the land,
России и освобождение крестьян с землёй
he was a follower of Fury
он был последователем Фурия всё
anyway, okay but good. And besides, for example, besides Dostoevsky, what
равно ладно а хорошо А кроме например
else did this period? So what
кроме достоевско чем ещ этот период Тода
do I see that the aristocracy of
что я получается смотрю что аристократия
the corner, the rest of the masses were a
угла остальные массы были
privileged society Yes, part  And the
привилегированное общество Да часть А
rest everyone lived in and, as it were, served as
остальное все жили в и как бы служили на
servants, that’s
обслугу это и
all. Well, yes, there was such a time. Well, where where in
всё Ну да было такое время Ну где где в
what state on the
каком государстве на
planet in a civilized one, that is, the euro,
планете в цивилизованном то есть евро по
like Europe or the then United
типу Европы или тогдашних Соединённых
States of America, you can say it wasn’t
Штатов Америки можно сказать не было
like that right? Yes, but why is that?  you are
такого правильно Да но почему вот вы
now already living in the century Yes, in your mind you’re
сейчас уже живя в веке Да мысленно вот
counting This is this system Yes in it it was
счита Вот это этот строй Да в де он был
better This is some kind of Golden Age
лучше Вот этот Золотой век какой-то
Why is this better in the sense because I’m
Почему так в смысле лучше потому что я
not saying that now we should go back
не говорю что сейчас мы должны вернуться
to the time of tsarism and you said everything for
во время царизма и всех за вы сказали
what is it when we started I asked yes you
что это когда мы начали Я спросил да вы
said that it was the best period
сказали что это был самый лучший период
Yes in the history of Russia and so on Well yes yes
Да в истории там России и так дальше Ну
well I started to understand By
да да ну я ж вот Начал чтоб понять По
what criteria Better you said
каким критериям Лучше вы сказали
Dostoevsky Yes I see That is, it
Достоевский Да я смотрю То есть
turns out as I see  I could be wrong,
получается как я вижу я могу ошибаться
but it seems to me, on the contrary, this regime
но мне кажется наоборот этот режим
prevented people like
препятствовал таким людям как
Dostoevsky because they were shot and
Достоевский потому что их расстреливали
thrown into hard labor. And so on,
скидывали в каторгу И так дальше они
instead of writing something, they
вместо того чтобы писать что-то Да они
cut down the forest somewhere in the taiga. Well, then
лес рубили где-то там в тайге Ну а потом
he wrote his
он написал свои
works which  were published
произведения которые были опубликованы
Well, well, if he had not been exiled, maybe
Ну хорошо А если бы его не сослали может
he somehow had more opportunity to
у него как-то больше было возможности
write, he would not have written those
писать он бы не написал бы те
works that
произведения кото
he would have written, some others were also
он бы другие какие-то написал тоже
cool, that is, well, look, a person
крутые то есть ну смотрите у человека
has a life, so part of his life is his
есть жизнь так часть его жизни его
he was sent to hard labor, he was sent to hard labor or
отправили на каторгу он на каторге или
after hard labor he wrote something there and it
после каторги что-то там написал и
turns out we are proud that he wrote about this
получается мы гордимся что О это он
because he was
написал вследствие того что его
sent to a boat. That’s cool
отправили на катер Вот круто
cool And what What I’m like I
круто И что Какой Вот вот я по како у
can’t understand what your question has to do with it
вас вопрос я не могу понять Причём тут
here is the king the empire is all that it is
вот царь империя это всё что что оно
positive for this it gave, it only
позитивное для этого дало оно же только
did something negative
делало
Well, if you judge like that, then probably the whole world
Ну если так посуди то наверное весь мир
was doing something negative at that time, not really.
делал негатив на тот момент не совсем
serfdom I don’t know
было такого крепостного права Не знаю
from some
ещё с каких-то
uh still probably a century
ээ ещё наверное столетия
or five If not more, that is, if
или пять Если ещё не больше то есть если
we look at the end of the 10th century then Well, when the
мы смотрим конец X века то Ну когда
steam steam engine was there
паровой паровой двигатель было оно
now John T, in my opinion, not John What’s
сейчас Джон Т по-моему не Джон А как
his name,
его так паровая
steam engine steam
машина паровой
engine here is James in 1769,
двигатель вот Джеймс у в 1769 году
look about 100 years before that Yes, while
смотри про 100 лет до этого Да пока
uh Dostoevsky was sent into exile Yes
ээ Достоевского в ссылку отправляли Да
100 years before that, for example in this in
100 лет до этого например в этом в
uh in Britain Yes, the
ээ в Британии Да
steam
вот паровой
engine
двигатель
was invented, that is, science technology
изобрели то есть там наука техника
flourished there Well, that is, people could And in
процветала Ну то есть люди могли А в
Russia, that is, did not prosper, prospered,
России то есть не процветала процветала
and that is, building the first planes
а то есть построение самолётов первых
there, what were the first planes?
там каких первых самолётов
Well,
Ну
skip who
прогули кто их
built them. Well, you skipped. I’m asking, I’m
строил Ну вы прогули Я спрашиваю мне
interested, look, your weapons were all
интересно смотри оружейка у вас была вся
imported. Yes, the Maxim machine gun, what’s that
импортная Да пулемёт Максима что так
called, you
называется
know? Well, so
знаете Ну что и
what, well, British or whatever  German
что ну британский или там немецки
Gunsmith
Оружейник
MASI kae the very road came from the West
МАСИ кае самоя дорога шла из Запада
developed For example, if we look at
развивала Вот например если мы смотрим
all the industrial enterprises
все промышленные предприятия
built by Western corporations If we
строили западные корпорации Если мы
look at modern Donetsk Yes, there was a use there
смотрим Донецк современный Да там юзовка
because John
была потому что Джон
Hughes, a Briton, mastered
Юз британец осваивал
these mining industries there And
эти горнодобывающие там промышленность А
what happened in Russia Russia was a backward
что было в России Россия была отсталой
country  When the first university
страной сри Когда первый университет
appeared in the Russian Empire,
появился в Российско империи
if I'm not
году если я не
mistaken. Perhaps, yes, yes, in
ошибаюсь Возможно да да в
St. Petersburg, before that, on the territory of
санкт-петербурге до этого на территории
Ukraine,
Украины уже действовала
the Kiev-Mogila Academy, Ostrog
киево-могилянская Академия острожская
Academy, was already operating. And in Europe, in general, you can’t count
Академия А в Европе вообще там не счесть
how many universities there have been since the 10th century.
сколько там с X с X века куча
there is
университетов было то есть
technologically Tsarist Russia was lagging behind, it’s
технологически отставала Царская Россия
just a
просто
shorter resource, there was just a lot of
короче ресурса было просто много
territory, wood, all sorts of coal and
территории дерева там всякого угля и
people. Well, what did Tsarist
людей Ну так а а что выпускала Царская
Russia produce using its
Россия на своих
technologies? Well, I’m telling you, google
технологиях Ну я вам говорю загуглите
about the development of aviation in the Russian
про развитие авиации в Российской
Empire, how is it? Let’s go with
империи как оно поло Давайте и
aviation, I’m
авиа меня же интересно
so interested  The Imperial Air Force
так Императорский военно-воздушный флот
formally existed in the twelfth and
формально существовал двенадцатый
seventeenth
семнадцатый
year,
год
that is, when we talk about the times of
всё то есть когда мы говорим про времена
Dostoevsky, there was not
Достоевского там в помине ещё не было
even a
даже
trace of it yet. In 1869,
никаких 1869
the commission considered the prospects for
году комиссия рассматривала перспективы
the use of transport in military
применения воз в военном
affairs in 1902, 903, this is already the beginning of the 20th
деле в 1902 903 год это уже начало XX
century in the Kiev military district  for the first time
века в киевском военном округе впервые
they used several
использовали несколько воздушных
balloons for conducting aerial reconnaissance and
шаров для ведения воздушной разведки и
adjusting artillery fire, where are the
корректировки огня артиллерии где тут
planes?
самолёты ну это выгу не так ят Я открыл
airships in the
империи э к изготовлению дирижабли в
Russian Empire began in 908
Российской империи приступили в 908 году
Where can I look about airplanes in the
Где я могу про самолёты посмотреть в
Russian
Российской
Empire on the Internet, well, well, I opened the
империи в интернете ну тож Я открыл
Internet where
интернет где
Look, well, look, you asked me a question.
Гля Ну смотрите я вы вопрос мне задали Я
I can’t know absolutely
вам я не могу знать абсолютно
everything for you, okay, let’s run further
всё ладно давай побегу дальше
then oh, I love it  all these imperials
тогда ой люблю я имперцев так всех этих
who hang flags. Well, you start
которые флаги вешают Да вот начинаешь
asking why the Empire attracts you.
спрашивать А чем тебя Империя привлекает
But then it was good and none
А вот тогда было хорошо и вот мне никто
of them can explain to me. Why
не может из них объяснить А чем же тогда
was it good then? relatives. By the way, if you can
было хорошо родственники Кстати если ты
hear me there, your relatives are
там слышишь меня да родственники твои
most likely relatives  The
скорее всего ка родственники
overwhelming majority of all other
подавляющего количество всех других
people who live now were
людей которые сейчас живут были
serfs. Then, when they were freed, the
крепостными Потом когда освободились
poor were Christians. Well, the Kurkuli
были бедовые христианами Ну там куркули
tried something, yes. But
что-то пробовали да А в
mostly the Russian Empire. Yes, it was a
основном Российская империя Да была
backward country. When Europe, Britain is
отсталой страной Когда Европа Британия
so technologically advanced. This is how we
настолько технологична Вот как сейчас мы
look now. Yes, this gap is technological. Yes,
смотрим Да этот разрыв технологический
computers are from there.  they go Yes, everything goes
Да компьютеры оттуда идут Да всё идёт
from there and so it was then we look, damn
оттуда так и тогда было мы смотрим блин
the planes, the balloon was launched Okay Let's
самолёты воздушный шар запускали Ладно
go
Идем
further, let's write like this, let's write someone who hasn't written yet before, please
дальше так пидпишить давайте кто Ще доси
deliver a like,
не писался до пидпишить доставьте лайк
crash, crumble, give a caption on mi and
рухайся рухайся дали пидпись на мий и
inst I don't know why this is for what is
inst Я не знаю для чого це тоб для чого
it there  marvel at otsey face Ale for
тоб там дивитись на оцей фейс Але для
you tse odi two or three clicks Ale ti
тебе це оди два або три клика Але ти
trimae mene and I will say in me there
тримае мене и я буду казати в мене там
Kupa fouls and in mene will be the best mood
Купа фолов и в мене буде класний настр
for Robi but cool video write on my inst
щоб Роби но крут видео пись на мий inst
Popik Andriy
Попик Андрий
So let me tekka
Так давай я тека
with
с